<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning on while true: continue</title>
    <link>http://jad-b.github.io/categories/learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learning on while true: continue</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 May 2016 07:42:13 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://jad-b.github.io/categories/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;m Not Getting My Graduate Degree (Yet).</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Why%20Not%20School/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2016 07:42:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Why%20Not%20School/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In case you &lt;em&gt;haven&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; heard, data science is big right now. And when you say
&amp;ldquo;data science&amp;rdquo; you also get &amp;ldquo;machine learning&amp;rdquo; packaged in for free, and that stuff&amp;rsquo;s
cool, so even better!  Plus, the booming field of data engineering is making
all &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of advances in dealing with Big Data, like real-time streaming from
massive amounts of data sources, and you can&amp;rsquo;t tell me that&amp;rsquo;s not going to be
necessity for the widgets of tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe, like me, you&amp;rsquo;d like to learn more about all of this. And perhaps,
like me, you&amp;rsquo;ve got a job, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty good job. But the knee-jerk
response you hear is, &amp;ldquo;Get your master&amp;rsquo;s degree&amp;rdquo;, or even further, a Ph.D. And
this is a problem. Not just the money&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:0dd3d526e46395327a1e0149bbb97370:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:0dd3d526e46395327a1e0149bbb97370:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or the potential move, or the
commitment, but the lack of &lt;em&gt;optimality&lt;/em&gt;: is this the best way to learn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much of your undergraduate education got left in a notebook, or existed
only for a test? Do you remember anything you didn&amp;rsquo;t actually apply? Did you
ever sit bored in class? How about completely lost (at least a more useful
feeling)? What a waste. You, or someone, &lt;em&gt;paid&lt;/em&gt; for that lost time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at what a modern &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/webhp?sourceid=chrome-instant&amp;amp;ion=1&amp;amp;espv=2&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8#q=define%20auto%20didact&#34;&gt;autodidact&lt;/a&gt; can utilize when learning data
science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take advantage of a broad selection of online courses to gain initial
exposure to concepts and an beginner to intermediate understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can buy textbooks, which are useful twice: once for their table of
contents to tell you what the field looks like, and again for when you need
the details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to essentially all academic literature, if and when that necessity arises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take advantage of a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of open-source software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get experience from Kaggle competitions, which have directly led to numerous
people getting jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a knock against all higher education. It is not. If your
goal is to research, or simply learn all you can about a topic, then I think
academia is the perfect, and perhaps only, option. And there are many things
going for higher-education: Direct access to experts and
prohibitively-expensive equipment, a guaranteed path, a like-minded community,
networking and institutional reputation, and job placement services at the end.
I believe each of those points has a self-learning counter-part, and that
comparison would deserve its own write-up, in the interest of keeping this
focused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself this: After a year of self-tutelage, would you be &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; off if
you &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; decided to start a graduate program? Or, as I believe, would you
find yourself a better student, questions in mind, with answers to satisfy?
The self-generated portfolio from your year of self-teaching would certainly
assist in admissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, you might find you don&amp;rsquo;t need that graduate&amp;rsquo;s program at all,
or that your interests have changed as a result of what you learned yourself.
No one knows you better than yourself. It won&amp;rsquo;t be easy. You&amp;rsquo;ll have to learn
how &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; learn: how to tell when you&amp;rsquo;ve dead-ended, when you&amp;rsquo;re coasting.
You&amp;rsquo;ll have to find your own projects. And you&amp;rsquo;ll have to manage your own
motivation, since you won&amp;rsquo;t have a course progression or grades to praise you.
These are hard things to do. They are also worthwhile things to do. You get to
take them with you the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am taking this path. It&amp;rsquo;s already been difficult. Progress feels like drawing
loops without lifting the pen from the page; you go forwards, then sideways,
then backwards, but you never end up where you started, and that becomes your
new starting point. I want to find more people embarking on this new form of
open, project-based, crowd-sourced, self-directed education, no matter their
field of interest. Hopefully our loops will cross paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this more for myself than anyone, but don&amp;rsquo;t we always?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:0dd3d526e46395327a1e0149bbb97370:1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because average annual tuition costs are $30-40k, and even with
50% financial aid, this is still tens of thousands of dollars. And you need
health insurance. And if you want to get it done fast, you&amp;rsquo;re almost certainly
not working, although a 2-year degree &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible if you commit the rest of
your non-working hours to school, with an associated hit to your quality of
life.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:0dd3d526e46395327a1e0149bbb97370:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>