<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Journals on while true: continue</title>
    <link>http://jad-b.github.io/journal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Journals on while true: continue</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 09:30:55 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://jad-b.github.io/journal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>2016Dec01 - Self-Study</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/journal/learning-2016Dec01/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 09:30:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/journal/learning-2016Dec01/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h5 id=&#34;takeaways:80d78c5218f8687004095bfb4a3d3a5e&#34;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning is a Bandit problem: Do you explore or exploit?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider learning broadly &amp;amp; iteratively, as opposed to deeply and sequentially&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There needs to be a heuristic for determining when to go &amp;ldquo;down&amp;rdquo;, and switch to more
fundamental material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I will study Introduction to Algorithms, 5.3. This calls for a review of
5.2, as well as whatever Anki prompts me for regarding 5.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, back to today&amp;rsquo;s studies: If I reflect, I feel I recall the lessons from 5.1
(two days ago) are still fresh, and I could easily re-write them if necessary.
5.2 would return with a modicum of effort, as one would expect being only a day
old. I prepare to study, I study, I create resources for review, I review, I do
problems. Still, when the time comes to do the problems, I often find them quite
puzzling. I perhaps under-estimated CLRS, since I&amp;rsquo;d already used it in my
undergraduate algorithm&amp;rsquo;s course. And, perhaps, time has stolen what easy
familiarity I had with statistics and calculus in the first place - or maybe
this is as good as I&amp;rsquo;ve ever been. Oh well; I know now what I know, there is no
other choice for a starting place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where I&amp;rsquo;m going with this is: do I need to take a step back, re-learn the basics
before attempting to progress? Given infinite time, I might re-take Algebra or
even Geometry to refresh all that has decayed with disuse. But infinite time
isn&amp;rsquo;t an option, and I&amp;rsquo;m presented with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-armed_bandit&#34;&gt;Multi-Armed Bandit problem&lt;/a&gt;: Do I
explore more avenues of learning, or do I exploit (study) what I&amp;rsquo;ve landed upon?
I had skipped reviewing the appendices A &amp;amp; C on Summations and Counting &amp;amp;
Probability; never too late to go back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night I spent some time finding recommended textbooks for Calculus and
Statistics from Quora. It was surprisingly fruitful; I&amp;rsquo;m quite excited for
several of the books I found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/dp/0914098918/ref=wl_it_dp_o_pC_nS_ttl?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;colid=3S5ZAOCXZJ47H&amp;amp;coliid=IMTWWBJDML1LI&#34;&gt;Calculus by Michael
Spivak&lt;/a&gt;
came highly recommended, at least twice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/dp/188652923X/ref=wl_it_dp_o_pC_nS_ttl?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;colid=3S5ZAOCXZJ47H&amp;amp;coliid=I21BQ7JLWUC58U&#34;&gt;Introduction to Probability, by Bertsekas &amp;amp;
Tsitsiklis&lt;/a&gt;
also showed up several times. It is the introductory probability book for MIT
&amp;amp; Stanford. The poster made an interesting distinction between probability and
statistics that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t before considered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/dp/1439840954/ref=wl_it_dp_o_pC_nS_ttl?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;colid=3S5ZAOCXZJ47H&amp;amp;coliid=IHYGHDNH1KDQF&#34;&gt;Bayesian Data Analysis, by
Gelman&lt;/a&gt;.
Recommended for applying Bayesian methods, but several reviews said it was
light on &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; you would do so. I expect to pair-read this with
another book on the topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings mostly came from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quora.com/What-are-some-good-online-courses-and-books-available-for-learning-probability-and-statistics/answer/Justin-Rising?srid=9cIW&#34;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;. I must confess to myself, I find the theory as interesting as the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How will I know to take a step back, and move to a different textbook? Maybe
expecting to complete a subject in one pass is silly; perhaps I should be
&lt;em&gt;expecting&lt;/em&gt; to revisit material, and bounce up-and-down its chain of
prerequisites as I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always haunted by the feeling there is a better way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>