<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on while true: continue</title>
    <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on while true: continue</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 10:03:36 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://jad-b.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Fitness</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Fitness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 10:03:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Fitness/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in human improvement for over a decade now, but I&amp;rsquo;d have to
say it started when I got into weight lifting. It&amp;rsquo;s such a perfect black-box:
input exercise, output personal improvement. We have not come so far as to
split off from our physical selves. I&amp;rsquo;ve progressed and regressed more than I
can keep track of, but I&amp;rsquo;ve (mostly) enjoyed the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How I learned, however, is not how I would recommend to another. I wasted much
time, over-trained, and picked up some injuries I&amp;rsquo;m sure to entertain for the
rest of my life due to ignorance of proper lifting technique and an
under-appreciation for mobility as a foundation for strength. I hope that by
collecting my thoughts, I will come to new conclusions, and find more
sustainable ways forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few criteria for any new action, and I steal here from Gray Cook:
Is it sustainable? Is it well-informed? Is there feedback? Positive answers to
these questions create maintainable, intelligent, adaptable systems. Those we
like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diagnosis-feedback:3e9cbc192015be8abad6cc78152eece0&#34;&gt;Diagnosis &amp;amp; Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stretching can inform your myofasical-release strategy. When stretching, focus
on exactly &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; within the muscle you feel tightness, and attack those areas
while foam rolling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes:3e9cbc192015be8abad6cc78152eece0&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t feel good after a workout, are you doing something wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performing muscle-focused work in a circuit has been working well.  Using the
rest periods to perform ancillary training (like grip strength) and stretching
fits those lesser priorities in without wasting time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we believe strength-training to be a skill, we can decompose the skill into
its component parts. At the bottom of this hierarchy, we arrive at the
contractions of singular muscles; at the top, the complete movement. At
intermediate steps, we have the composite movements that make up the larger
movement. How can we routinely and analytically decompose a movement?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coffee.</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Coffee/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Coffee/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A jittery and slightly abusive love story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel absurd writing this, but I&amp;rsquo;m not sure coffe and I are meant to be
together. We always start out so good; that first cup in the morning gets my
mind going, and I mean &lt;em&gt;going&lt;/em&gt;. Holy shit, the ideas that come into my
head&amp;hellip;and the sheer &lt;em&gt;quantity&lt;/em&gt;, I mean, just &lt;em&gt;dozens&lt;/em&gt;. And that&amp;rsquo;s any given
morning! Plus, the world seems so much more&amp;hellip;&lt;em&gt;conquerable&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;ldquo;I can learn
front-end web development, calculus, machine learning, review my algorithms
textbook, and graphics programming simulatanesouly; I just need good time
management!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But coffee soon starts looking more like a siren than a muse. My carefully-laid
schedule, built to lay brick-by-brick of foundational knowledge and skill
towards my master plan, gets thrown out the window by sudden insights and
fervently-important tangents. Hell, these very words are due to coffee! I didn&amp;rsquo;t
mean to write about my shitty relationship with coffee! I was gonna study
probability! God-&lt;em&gt;dammit&lt;/em&gt;. Plus, I don&amp;rsquo;t think my insides, how to say,
&lt;em&gt;accomodates&lt;/em&gt; coffee very well. It&amp;rsquo;s sneaky though; sometimes it takes a few
days. Of course, I usually lose my god-damned mind and &amp;ldquo;1 cup in the morning,
and only after breakfast&amp;rdquo; turns into &amp;ldquo;2 cups, then some decaf, and oh shit I
didn&amp;rsquo;t eat anything and now it&amp;rsquo;s dinner&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know where I&amp;rsquo;m going with this. It makes me feel great, and I&amp;rsquo;ve had
some genuine breakthroughs that I attribute at least in part to coffee. I used
to think my body thought it was poison, but it could just as easily be my
inability to consume it responsibly; a cup after eating may be fine, but three
cups on an empty stomach not so much (writing that out begs a &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;sans
excrement&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pros:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking up &lt;a href=&#34;https://examine.com/supplements/Caffeine/&#34;&gt;Caffeine on examine.com&lt;/a&gt;
eventually links to articles&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that show caffeine consumed &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; learning can
aid in memory consolidation. Interestingly, no benefit is shown when coffee is
drank &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the good ideas &lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;. Valuable in my line of work and hobbies (which look a
lot like my line of work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of physical performance benefits are associated with caffeine: Training
volume, lactate production, power creation. You&amp;rsquo;d be a &lt;em&gt;fool&lt;/em&gt; not to use some!
But tea provides caffeine as well as coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some evidence that coffee (or caffeine; it&amp;rsquo;s hard to pull them apart) helps with
the &amp;ldquo;tip-of-the-tongue&amp;rdquo; effect, i.e. recall by association. Very helpful; I just
remembered I wanted to buy &amp;ldquo;Why Zebras Don&amp;rsquo;t Get Ulcers&amp;rdquo; for my girlfriend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cons:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makes it &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more likely my emotions get the better of my good sense, and
that may be the worst sin of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems to suppress my appetite. I am not a guy who needs his appetite suppressed,
so this is a major negative. However, this may only be when I drink coffe on an
empty stomach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly linked to some GI distress? See above note on coffee-before-or-after
food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Browns your teeth. Seriously though, now you&amp;rsquo;ve got something else to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can make me more irritable, and short with people in general, and no likes a
cranky me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can lead to greater anxiety, which can reinforce other stressors, and
&lt;em&gt;stress&lt;/em&gt; is a sure way to slowly ruin everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;verdict:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda&#34;&gt;Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like coffee. I feel like the answer lies in me figuring out its place
in my life, which sounds like in the morning, around 10, after I&amp;rsquo;ve eaten and
done my morning studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/the-curious-wavefunction/should-you-drink-coffee-before-or-after-a-learning-task/&#34;&gt;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/the-curious-wavefunction/should-you-drink-coffee-before-or-after-a-learning-task/&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic Graphical Models</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Probabilistic%20Graphical%20Models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2016 20:27:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Probabilistic%20Graphical%20Models/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;resources:8cad16868491a664b3f3011901d2cf61&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.116.7467&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&#34;&gt;Introduction to Graphical Models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://web4.cs.ucl.ac.uk/staff/D.Barber/textbook/181115.pdf&#34;&gt;Bayesian Reasoning and Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~epxing/Class/10708-16/&#34;&gt;CMU&amp;rsquo;s Probabilistic Graphical Models, Spring 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-[_blank_] Modeling</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Multi-_%20Modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2016 10:26:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Multi-_%20Modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multilevel models are statistical models of parameters that vary at more than one level. - source: [Multilevel model:wikipedia].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This implies that the same parameters can take different values amongst sibling models of different parents. To
illustrate, let&amp;rsquo;s work through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multilevel_model#Example&#34;&gt;example given in wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic linear regression model for predicting income may take age, class, gender, and race as parameters:
&lt;code&gt;$f(age,class,gender,race) = income$&lt;/code&gt;. However, this is likely to predict the same income for a 45-year old black man in
Seattle, WA as it would for one in Mobile, AL. A simple way to attempt account for this would be to determine the &lt;em&gt;bias&lt;/em&gt;
for each location, and add or subtract that from the estimated income. However, it&amp;rsquo;s obvious this is pretty naive; it
attempts to account for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the differences between locations by a fixed value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A multilevel model allows our parameters of age, class, gender, and race, to take different values per location, by
adding location as a level to our model. Now, our income estimators are scoped by location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s still assumed that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; values for each parameters are drawn from a shared underlying distribution. To explain,
consider all the values we&amp;rsquo;d likely learn to explain the impact of age, a.k.a the coefficient for the age parameter,
a.k.a &lt;code&gt;$\theta_{age}Age$&lt;/code&gt;. Let&amp;rsquo;s pretend that the bigger the location, the more age benefits you; population will be
proportional to the value with which we weight age, &lt;code&gt;$\theta_{age}Age$&lt;/code&gt;. As there are more people in urban areas,
the distribution of age coefficients will be weighted towards the higher end to reflect that
&lt;em&gt;in general&lt;/em&gt;, people make more as they get older.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll posit that people make more as they get older. We could even pretend it&amp;rsquo;s a linear relationship, as simple as
&lt;code&gt;$income = poverty_line + \theta_{age}Age$&lt;/code&gt;. Now, what if we observe that people in cities make &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt; as they get
older than people who aren&amp;rsquo;t? And, it turns out, that a majority of older (50+) people live in cities? Well, that means
the values we&amp;rsquo;re calculating to weight the impact of age, a.k.a the age coefficients, a.k.a &lt;code&gt;$\theta_{age}$&lt;/code&gt;,
will reward age more heavily than if the majority of older people &lt;em&gt;weren&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; in cities. So the distribution of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
the age coefficients, &lt;code&gt;$\theta_{age}$&lt;/code&gt; we&amp;rsquo;ll learn per location will favor age, up to a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multilevel models are subclasses of Hierarchical Bayesian Models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select between models using Bayesian|Akakike Information Criteria (the equivalent of &lt;code&gt;score()&lt;/code&gt; in sklearn.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons Learned: Software</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Lessons%20Learned:%20Software/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2016 09:59:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Lessons%20Learned:%20Software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use TLS from the beginning.&lt;/strong&gt;
There aren&amp;rsquo;t many reasons you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t. Snakeoil gets you in the practice of
managing the keys, but a self-signed or corporate wildcard cert that&amp;rsquo;s scoped
to your development domain are even better. I&amp;rsquo;m finally seeing a plethora of
key management tools&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:fe4463e88dd1ddad3485337b6892122f:kmt&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:fe4463e88dd1ddad3485337b6892122f:kmt&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; begin to propagate, so no excuses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write functional tests to run against any envinromnet.&lt;/strong&gt;
This means they need to accept configuration options, and should only
affect test data they&amp;rsquo;re responsible for creating and deleting. Now your
integration tests can smoke-test production.
If you can scope which tests run, which I know Python&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;nose&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;pytest&lt;/code&gt;
and Golang&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;go test -tags=smoke&lt;/code&gt; can do, you can limit your tests to fit
your requirements of run time, data safety, and validation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incremental modifications over re-writes.&lt;/strong&gt;
You have code running, and now you need to change it. It&amp;rsquo;s conceptually
easiest to pretend like that code doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, and write from scratch.
But only in concept. Re-writes ignore the ecosystem that code runs within -
the system&amp;rsquo;s that depend on it, the operational considerations you&amp;rsquo;ve learned to
account for, and the realities of the world you&amp;rsquo;ve had to code around.
Re-writes have a place. But they&amp;rsquo;re usually the harder choice, long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s some ideas I&amp;rsquo;ve already had to use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget about search &amp;amp; replace. Rename old objects to
&amp;ldquo;OldStructure&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;StructureV1&amp;rdquo; while the deprecation is underway.
People seem to get nervous about this, but if you missed something, a
static language won&amp;rsquo;t compile, and a dynamically-typed language will have
its tests fail. If both of those fail to catch the error, is it really a
problem with the replacement, or with your safety nets?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;REST API: Isolate the old and new logic into different functions. Deploy
new changes to a &amp;ldquo;dark&amp;rdquo; endoint under a different path. Toggle between
old &amp;amp; new using a query parameter, or swap them at runtime using a flag.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Database: Adding new columns is easy. Modifying existing requires
staggered deploys between the DB and its clients (probably your
downstream API(s)). Sorry.  At some point, you will be faced with the
choice of doing a total re-write, followed by a nerve-wracking deploy,
replete with cross-team coordination, or biting off that complexity in
small changes and frequent deployments. Small changes let you deploy
faster. Deploying faster =&amp;gt; Your work affects people faster. Mattering in
other people&amp;rsquo;s lives =&amp;gt; putting off existential meaningless for one more
day. Search &amp;ldquo;zero-downtime DB migration&amp;rdquo; for plenty of resources. I&amp;rsquo;m
partial to the outline in Chapter 12 of &amp;ldquo;Continuous Delivery&amp;rdquo; by Jez
Humble, titled &amp;ldquo;Managing Data&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write backwards from your user interfaces&lt;/strong&gt;.
Writing a web app? Start with the UI. You&amp;rsquo;re writing the REST API the UI calls?
Start with the API description. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/OAI/OpenAPI-Specification&#34;&gt;OpenAPI is a thing now&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;m not going
back. It&amp;rsquo;s a CLI tool? Write the options w/ flags, for what you know you
need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only write for what someone needs right now. What someone wants but not needs
should live in a design conversation elsewhere, such as a GitHub issue, a
text document, or a JIRA ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this to be a (correct) generalization of &amp;ldquo;API-first&amp;rdquo; design and/or
contract-driven design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible argument: This delays potentially deal-breaking backend
considerations that are far-removed from the end-user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think two things are imporant to keep in mind. First, your problem has
likely been solved before, many times over. This is the case for most
full-stack work. Thus, the amount of &amp;ldquo;unknowns&amp;rdquo; lurking out there
are few, and always getting smaller. Second, all this really means is you
have a conversation with your clients (The web UI team) exactly when you were
actually building the tool they wanted. If anyone has examples of a tool
simply can&amp;rsquo;t be made human-friendlier, I&amp;rsquo;d be interested to know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:fe4463e88dd1ddad3485337b6892122f:kmt&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Such as these:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/kms/&#34;&gt;Amazon KMS&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vaultproject.io/docs/secrets/pki/index.html&#34;&gt;Hashicorp&amp;rsquo;s Vault&amp;rsquo;s PKI Backend&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/square/certstrap&#34;&gt;Square&amp;rsquo;s certstrap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:fe4463e88dd1ddad3485337b6892122f:kmt&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;m Not Getting My Graduate Degree (Yet).</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Why%20Not%20School/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2016 07:42:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Why%20Not%20School/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In case you &lt;em&gt;haven&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; heard, data science is big right now. And when you say
&amp;ldquo;data science&amp;rdquo; you also get &amp;ldquo;machine learning&amp;rdquo; packaged in for free, and that stuff&amp;rsquo;s
cool, so even better!  Plus, the booming field of data engineering is making
all &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of advances in dealing with Big Data, like real-time streaming from
massive amounts of data sources, and you can&amp;rsquo;t tell me that&amp;rsquo;s not going to be
necessity for the widgets of tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe, like me, you&amp;rsquo;d like to learn more about all of this. And perhaps,
like me, you&amp;rsquo;ve got a job, and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty good job. But the knee-jerk
response you hear is, &amp;ldquo;Get your master&amp;rsquo;s degree&amp;rdquo;, or even further, a Ph.D. And
this is a problem. Not just the money&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:0dd3d526e46395327a1e0149bbb97370:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:0dd3d526e46395327a1e0149bbb97370:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, or the potential move, or the
commitment, but the lack of &lt;em&gt;optimality&lt;/em&gt;: is this the best way to learn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much of your undergraduate education got left in a notebook, or existed
only for a test? Do you remember anything you didn&amp;rsquo;t actually apply? Did you
ever sit bored in class? How about completely lost (at least a more useful
feeling)? What a waste. You, or someone, &lt;em&gt;paid&lt;/em&gt; for that lost time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at what a modern &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/webhp?sourceid=chrome-instant&amp;amp;ion=1&amp;amp;espv=2&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8#q=define%20auto%20didact&#34;&gt;autodidact&lt;/a&gt; can utilize when learning data
science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take advantage of a broad selection of online courses to gain initial
exposure to concepts and an beginner to intermediate understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can buy textbooks, which are useful twice: once for their table of
contents to tell you what the field looks like, and again for when you need
the details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to essentially all academic literature, if and when that necessity arises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take advantage of a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of open-source software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get experience from Kaggle competitions, which have directly led to numerous
people getting jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a knock against all higher education. It is not. If your
goal is to research, or simply learn all you can about a topic, then I think
academia is the perfect, and perhaps only, option. And there are many things
going for higher-education: Direct access to experts and
prohibitively-expensive equipment, a guaranteed path, a like-minded community,
networking and institutional reputation, and job placement services at the end.
I believe each of those points has a self-learning counter-part, and that
comparison would deserve its own write-up, in the interest of keeping this
focused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself this: After a year of self-tutelage, would you be &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; off if
you &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; decided to start a graduate program? Or, as I believe, would you
find yourself a better student, questions in mind, with answers to satisfy?
The self-generated portfolio from your year of self-teaching would certainly
assist in admissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, of course, you might find you don&amp;rsquo;t need that graduate&amp;rsquo;s program at all,
or that your interests have changed as a result of what you learned yourself.
No one knows you better than yourself. It won&amp;rsquo;t be easy. You&amp;rsquo;ll have to learn
how &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; learn: how to tell when you&amp;rsquo;ve dead-ended, when you&amp;rsquo;re coasting.
You&amp;rsquo;ll have to find your own projects. And you&amp;rsquo;ll have to manage your own
motivation, since you won&amp;rsquo;t have a course progression or grades to praise you.
These are hard things to do. They are also worthwhile things to do. You get to
take them with you the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am taking this path. It&amp;rsquo;s already been difficult. Progress feels like drawing
loops without lifting the pen from the page; you go forwards, then sideways,
then backwards, but you never end up where you started, and that becomes your
new starting point. I want to find more people embarking on this new form of
open, project-based, crowd-sourced, self-directed education, no matter their
field of interest. Hopefully our loops will cross paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this more for myself than anyone, but don&amp;rsquo;t we always?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:0dd3d526e46395327a1e0149bbb97370:1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because average annual tuition costs are $30-40k, and even with
50% financial aid, this is still tens of thousands of dollars. And you need
health insurance. And if you want to get it done fast, you&amp;rsquo;re almost certainly
not working, although a 2-year degree &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible if you commit the rest of
your non-working hours to school, with an associated hit to your quality of
life.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:0dd3d526e46395327a1e0149bbb97370:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gradient Descent: Ascending</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Gradient%20Descent%20Ascending/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 07:20:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Gradient%20Descent%20Ascending/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradient descent keeps ascending my cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Funny story&lt;/em&gt;, the issue wasn&amp;rsquo;t with the gradient descent implementation at all, but rather
the cost function(least squares). I was calculating my error by subtracting my
predicted values from the actual values(y), &lt;code&gt;$error = predicted - y$&lt;/code&gt;, instead of the other
way around, &lt;code&gt;$ error = y - predicted$&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This washed out when it came to calculating cost, since you end up squaring the error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;$$
    J(\theta) = \frac{1}{2m}\sum_{i=1}^m(h_{\theta}(x^{i}) - y^{i})^{2}
$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but it &lt;em&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; get squared when you calculate the gradient:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;$$
    \theta_{j} := \alpha\frac{1}{m}\sum_{i=1}^m (h_{\theta}(x^{(i)})-y^{(i)})x_{j}^{(i)}
$$&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Aggressive Student</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/The%20Aggressive%20Student/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2016 09:55:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/The%20Aggressive%20Student/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Learning is being in a race against yourself. These things help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-rapid-acquisistion-of-highly-technical-information:04d7ba831a5d03aab2a2b90cdbe484ff&#34;&gt;The Rapid Acquisistion of Highly-Technical Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning very technical information is unique from the general problem of
learning in a few ways. First of all, the end-result is entirely mental. Either
you understand the concepts well enough to accomplish your task, or you do not.
This is in contrast to learning a song on the piano, where a subconscious system
is learning instead, like training motor patterns for rote memorization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine your current state of skill or knowledge as a wavefront. Inside its
boundary is your &amp;ldquo;known&amp;rdquo;, and outside is the &amp;ldquo;unknown&amp;rdquo;.
Your awareness of an Unknown item is determined by its distance from the
boundary of this wavefront.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few corollaries:
1) You can only learn what lies against this wavefront.
2) You can &amp;ldquo;reach&amp;rdquo; into the Unknown by attempting (and failing) to
This &amp;ldquo;reaching&amp;rdquo; is defined by your failure to completely learn; otherwise,
you&amp;rsquo;d be at step one. However, this primes you to learn the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine casting a net around a topic you don&amp;rsquo;t understand. The &amp;ldquo;net&amp;rdquo; is made of
all the possible connections you can make to this topic; previous training,
analogy to other fields, half-notions of concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-it-feels:04d7ba831a5d03aab2a2b90cdbe484ff&#34;&gt;How it feels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important feelings I can associate with learning are boredom,
frustration, confusion, and flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boredom tells you the work is too easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frustration says you are missing something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confusion says you have over-reached. This is only a bad thing in large
amounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flow says you&amp;rsquo;ve got it just right. It lies between boredom and confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sequencing-when-to-learn-what:04d7ba831a5d03aab2a2b90cdbe484ff&#34;&gt;Sequencing | When to Learn What&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the highest-level summary of the topic you can. Then a slightly more
verbose description. Then yet another more verbosity write-up. Etc., etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When in doubt, jump in. Write down what confuses you. Keep going until the
confusion reaches a point that you can no longer pretend to know what&amp;rsquo;s going
on. The list you&amp;rsquo;ve written is where you&amp;rsquo;ll start tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;spacing-when-to-learn:04d7ba831a5d03aab2a2b90cdbe484ff&#34;&gt;Spacing | When to Learn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn until one of these two things happen: You feel confused, or you&amp;rsquo;ve
grasped a new topic but wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to teach it well yourself. This is
where you&amp;rsquo;ll pick up from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you revisit topics, mix in sources. If you began your exploration with an
online course, try: A blog post, a YouTube video, a textbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day after learning, review your notes.  The next day, summarize them. Where
possible, use drawings and analogy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;basic-tips:04d7ba831a5d03aab2a2b90cdbe484ff&#34;&gt;Basic tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only highlight/underline what you don&amp;rsquo;t understand. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t help you
remember, but it does help you find the gaps when you revisit the material.
Use some kind of notation for removing highlights as you do comprehend the
gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A System for Learning</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/A%20Learning%20System/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/A%20Learning%20System/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What would the ideal learning system look like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ties into external sources of information

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Needs data citation format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Videos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Textbooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online articles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assists you while learning&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre-study preparation

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the problem, and why does it matter?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prompt to skim the material&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prompt to develop questions before starting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read someone else&amp;rsquo;s Feynman Technique explanation as a warm-up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study dashboard

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Times how long you study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unknowns (Search bar + record as a prerequisite)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-study

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asks &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; to develop review questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assists during Review&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses crowdsourced review questions to primer your review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provides a space for you to use the Feynman technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provides hints as needed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manages scheduling your review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Randomize review order&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assists during application&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use previous explanations to assist in review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, show problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st hint: Show key points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2nd hint: Show verbal walkthrough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3rd hint: Show solution in entirety

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disable copy-paste (if possible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time-limit each hint to encourage participation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Learning</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/On%20Learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/On%20Learning/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-optimize-learning:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Why Optimize Learning?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why spend time learning &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to learn, instead of just learning what you want?
What are the problems we overcome when learning? What are our goals?
What are the short and long-term benefits from optimizing how we learn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-to-learn:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;How to Learn&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;figuring-out-what-to-learn:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Figuring Out What to Learn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guess at a topic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overreach

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify what you&amp;rsquo;re confused by.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write down every word, concept, and reference you don&amp;rsquo;t understand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the prerequisite concepts for what confuses you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat until you&amp;rsquo;re on known ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gather resources

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify at least three resources. Each should take a different
approach: different wording, different examples, different formats
(slide deck, pdf, video, q&amp;amp;a).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scope the material

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Table of contents from textbooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syllabus from a college course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progression of a YouTube video series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-study:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;How to Study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learn:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Learn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Optional) These may help in getting more out of a session.

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guess at Why it matters, and What problem it solves.  1. Look at some problems beforehand 1. Come up with questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warm-up by skimming the material, or reading a higher-level resource like
slides or an introductory text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note your start time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Optional) Set a timer. This can help focus you on the task at hand.
You may want to set enough time aside to perform a wrap-up of your notes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note questions and missing prerequisites as you go.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jargon you need to define, statements you don&amp;rsquo;t understand, completely mysterious
concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write, like with a pen, down difficult sections to work through. Writing
shows superior assistance in retention over typing&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consume material until confused (%50 comprehension), or out of time.

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note your end time, and calculate your adjusted velocity:
(pages read / time spent) * % comprehension = pg/min&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;review:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Review&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempt to recall material before referring to external resources.

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outlining key concepts can assist in reminding you what you learned.
It can also help for classifying the concept.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every review, attempt to re-summarize what you wrote previously. Eventually
contain it down to a sentence or two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use your list of questions you built while learning to lookup answers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indicate relationships to other topics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a system, like Anki SRS, for long-term memorization

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rs.io/anki-tips/&#34;&gt;http://rs.io/anki-tips/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/medicalschool/comments/4ocdyb/a_list_of_anki_tips_and_suggestions_that_i_wrote/&#34;&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/medicalschool/comments/4ocdyb/a_list_of_anki_tips_and_suggestions_that_i_wrote/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lessons-learned:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t learn faster than you can review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-template:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Study Template&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By following the below template, you perform the critical actions needed to
enhance your understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##### Before
What&#39;s the problem)

Why is this a problem?)

**Action: Skim material**

Theme of HW Problems)

Initial Questions)

##### During
**Action: Start timer**

Key Concepts)

Relationships)

Notes)

Questions)

Unknowns)

##### After
**Action: Stop timer**

Review Questions)

Feynman)

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-apply:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;How to Apply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lessons-learned-1:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing problems is insufficient as a review, but, for some reason, critical for
developing a complete understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;doing-problems:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Doing Problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discovery: Read the problems, w/o attempting to solve them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding: Read the problems, and solve them in a high-level way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remembering: Solve the problems which you deem to give you the most value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apply the five methods from CCtI:
1. Examplify: Write out examples, look for the pattern
2. Pattern Matching: What is the problem similar to?
3. Simplify &amp;amp; Generalize: Solve a simpler version of the problem, then abstract
   it to solve the larger case.
4. Base Case &amp;amp; Build: Solve the problem for a single element. Think &amp;ldquo;recursion&amp;rdquo;.
5. Data Structure Brainstorm: Try to apply every data structure you can think of
   until something sticks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;apply:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Apply&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin by conducting a Review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solve problems or build something

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a timer to focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cap at 30 minutes. If still unsolved, look up the solution, but reschedule as
it like any other problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q.&lt;/strong&gt; Scheduling: How often should problems be worked? Re-worked?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;talking-to-myself:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Talking to myself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;on-homework-problems:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;On Homework Problems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember spending the summer before my senior year doing hundreds of chemistry
problems, as assigned to me by my AP Chemistry teacher. For weeks straight, I
spent hours a day churning through them. Did I come to understand stoichoimetry?
Uh huh. And it&amp;rsquo;s with experiences like this, and the continuing assignment of
homework in school, that makes me think doing homework &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; increase
understanding. But where do the diminishing returns lie?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since hearing Ben Vigoda mention off-hand during an OSCON 2015 presentation
on probabilistic programming that research has shown humans can learn to
recognize a new object after about 3-5 exposures, I&amp;rsquo;ve wondered if there&amp;rsquo;s a bit
of magic to that range. Coupling that with phenomenon like Spaced Repetition for
studying, can we arrive at a approximately-optimal solution for studying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we can. Say you&amp;rsquo;re reading a textbook split into chapters, with sections
within those chapters. I propose a schedule like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day one) Read the first section of the first chapter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day two) Read the second section, and do 2-3 problems from the first section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day three) Read the third section, do 2-3 problems from the second section,
and 1 problem from the first section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day four) Read fourth section; 2 problems from third, 1 problem from second&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day five) Chapter&amp;rsquo;s finished; do 2 end-of-chapter problems, 2 fourth section
problems, 1 third section problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can view the schedule as a table, with rows of topics, columns of dates, and
cells holding the action you took to learn. The action could be solving a
problem, reading a section, or reviewing your notes; intuitively, it makes sense
to read the material, work on some problems, and save review for the long game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem&amp;rsquo;s been defined; how can we automate? At its simplest, we have an
ever-growing queue of work that needs to be scheduled at some point in the
future. There&amp;rsquo;s also a hierarchy amongst topics that we&amp;rsquo;ll want to leverage; obviously
the sections of a chapter are grouped together for a reason. Come a year from
now, we want our review to be focused on the &lt;em&gt;chapter&lt;/em&gt;, not on problem 4.2-5.
Indeed, the problems are simply tools for the much more valuable concepts they
engage us with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SuperMemo has a distinction between &lt;em&gt;topics&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;items&lt;/em&gt; which I think applies
here. To a point, we can treat the structure recursively; scholarly fields keep
their information in textbooks, which have chapters, which have sections. At the
lowest point, we must distinguish between the tools we use to learn at the
topics we wish to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-measure:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;How to Measure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-collection:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Data Collection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topic of section/chapter/textbook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time spent reading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of pages read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;% comprehension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watching

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time of video v. time spent watching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;% comprehension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topic of video/video series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;# of notes taken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;# of questions raised&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;# of unknowns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality of material (1-10 ranking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;quick-reference:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Quick Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warm-up

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the problem? Why does it matter?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(If Applicable) Review problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come up with additional questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skim material or warm-up with alt. introductory material&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a timer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write down questions and unknowns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work through difficult sections by hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write-up what you learned

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempt to recall from memory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outline key concepts to assist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Feynman Technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summarize previous reviews.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note relationships to other topics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lookup answers to questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create Anki cards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform a review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a timer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;other-methodologies:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Other Methodologies&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-read-a-book:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;How to Read a Book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;discover-inspectional:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Discover (Inspectional)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discern the &lt;em&gt;structure&lt;/em&gt; by reading the key elements

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highlight what &lt;em&gt;seem to be&lt;/em&gt; key points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Answer key questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is the author?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the book&amp;rsquo;s arguments?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the evidence that supports these?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are the book&amp;rsquo;s conclusions?
1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;understand-analytical:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Understand (Analytical)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Re-read, taking more time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attempt to answer questions from the Discover phase&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;remember:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Remember&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consolidate your notes about the assumptions, arguments, evidence, and
conclusions. Sort of like a Feynman, but with more detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a &lt;strong&gt;rehearsal schedule&lt;/strong&gt;, using notes that &lt;em&gt;you&amp;rsquo;ve&lt;/em&gt; determined to be
key from your readings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-feriss-disss:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Time Feriss&amp;rsquo; DiSSS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sq3r:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;SQ3R&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-can-we-learn-fron-teachers:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;What Can We Learn Fron Teachers?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;harvard-university-s-teaching-for-understanding-project-zero:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Harvard University&amp;rsquo;s Teaching for Understanding/Project Zero&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;berkely-the-how-students-learn-project:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Berkely: The How Students Learn Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;good-quotes:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468&#34;&gt;Good Quotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and what matters most is Understanding. And Understanding starts with &amp;ldquo;What Matters&amp;rdquo; - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quora.com/How-do-I-get-started-in-Artificial-Intelligence&#34;&gt;Quora:
Forays into AI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;because we get better with practice as we get more experience, which is a
hallmark of any Intuition based skill - &lt;a href=&#34;http://syntience.com/rch.pdf&#34;&gt;Reductionism Considered Harmful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another hallmark of Intuition based skills: they cannot be taught as
high level rules, they have to be experienced bottom up. This is,
incidentally, also the difference between Teaching and Coaching - [ibid]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgetting what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned from a class is not the course&amp;rsquo;s fault. Without
spaced, repetitive recall, no memories will be formed. - [me]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[grounding]: to give (something abstract) a firm theoretical or practical basis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468:1&#34;&gt;Ref needed.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7a16559f2e7bb44f60862eae17319468:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>