<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Health on while true: continue</title>
    <link>http://jad-b.github.io/categories/health/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Health on while true: continue</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://jad-b.github.io/categories/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Coffee.</title>
      <link>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Coffee/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jad-b.github.io/post/Coffee/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A jittery and slightly abusive love story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel absurd writing this, but I&amp;rsquo;m not sure coffe and I are meant to be
together. We always start out so good; that first cup in the morning gets my
mind going, and I mean &lt;em&gt;going&lt;/em&gt;. Holy shit, the ideas that come into my
head&amp;hellip;and the sheer &lt;em&gt;quantity&lt;/em&gt;, I mean, just &lt;em&gt;dozens&lt;/em&gt;. And that&amp;rsquo;s any given
morning! Plus, the world seems so much more&amp;hellip;&lt;em&gt;conquerable&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;ldquo;I can learn
front-end web development, calculus, machine learning, review my algorithms
textbook, and graphics programming simulatanesouly; I just need good time
management!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But coffee soon starts looking more like a siren than a muse. My carefully-laid
schedule, built to lay brick-by-brick of foundational knowledge and skill
towards my master plan, gets thrown out the window by sudden insights and
fervently-important tangents. Hell, these very words are due to coffee! I didn&amp;rsquo;t
mean to write about my shitty relationship with coffee! I was gonna study
probability! God-&lt;em&gt;dammit&lt;/em&gt;. Plus, I don&amp;rsquo;t think my insides, how to say,
&lt;em&gt;accomodates&lt;/em&gt; coffee very well. It&amp;rsquo;s sneaky though; sometimes it takes a few
days. Of course, I usually lose my god-damned mind and &amp;ldquo;1 cup in the morning,
and only after breakfast&amp;rdquo; turns into &amp;ldquo;2 cups, then some decaf, and oh shit I
didn&amp;rsquo;t eat anything and now it&amp;rsquo;s dinner&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know where I&amp;rsquo;m going with this. It makes me feel great, and I&amp;rsquo;ve had
some genuine breakthroughs that I attribute at least in part to coffee. I used
to think my body thought it was poison, but it could just as easily be my
inability to consume it responsibly; a cup after eating may be fine, but three
cups on an empty stomach not so much (writing that out begs a &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;sans
excrement&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pros:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking up &lt;a href=&#34;https://examine.com/supplements/Caffeine/&#34;&gt;Caffeine on examine.com&lt;/a&gt;
eventually links to articles&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that show caffeine consumed &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; learning can
aid in memory consolidation. Interestingly, no benefit is shown when coffee is
drank &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the good ideas &lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;. Valuable in my line of work and hobbies (which look a
lot like my line of work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of physical performance benefits are associated with caffeine: Training
volume, lactate production, power creation. You&amp;rsquo;d be a &lt;em&gt;fool&lt;/em&gt; not to use some!
But tea provides caffeine as well as coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some evidence that coffee (or caffeine; it&amp;rsquo;s hard to pull them apart) helps with
the &amp;ldquo;tip-of-the-tongue&amp;rdquo; effect, i.e. recall by association. Very helpful; I just
remembered I wanted to buy &amp;ldquo;Why Zebras Don&amp;rsquo;t Get Ulcers&amp;rdquo; for my girlfriend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cons:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makes it &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more likely my emotions get the better of my good sense, and
that may be the worst sin of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems to suppress my appetite. I am not a guy who needs his appetite suppressed,
so this is a major negative. However, this may only be when I drink coffe on an
empty stomach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly linked to some GI distress? See above note on coffee-before-or-after
food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Browns your teeth. Seriously though, now you&amp;rsquo;ve got something else to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can make me more irritable, and short with people in general, and no likes a
cranky me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can lead to greater anxiety, which can reinforce other stressors, and
&lt;em&gt;stress&lt;/em&gt; is a sure way to slowly ruin everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;verdict:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda&#34;&gt;Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like coffee. I feel like the answer lies in me figuring out its place
in my life, which sounds like in the morning, around 10, after I&amp;rsquo;ve eaten and
done my morning studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/the-curious-wavefunction/should-you-drink-coffee-before-or-after-a-learning-task/&#34;&gt;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/the-curious-wavefunction/should-you-drink-coffee-before-or-after-a-learning-task/&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:b19e3c9cdce88e87786a6b10c5d3deda:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>